A Guide to the Andrew J. Brent Papers, 1960-1988
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Andrew J. Brent Papers, 1960-1988
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 281
11.7 linear feet
Andrew J. Brent
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department by Mr. Brent in several installments.
Biographical/Historical Information
Andrew J. Brent was a Richmond attorney who was active in community affairs in the city. He was also former director, general counsel and secretary of Media General Inc., the firm that owns the Richmond Times- Dispatch and other media outlets in the southeast.
"He was instrumental in the establishment [in 1969] of Media General," said J. Steward Bryan III, publisher of the Richmond Times-Dispatch and chairman of Media General Inc. "In the mid-1960s, he was architect of the charter and by-laws of our company. The latter years of his life were devoted to metropolitan Richmond. He will be sorely missed, but his accomplishments will live on for decades to come."
A native of Richmond, Brent was born in 1919. He received his undergraduate degree from the University of Virginia and graduated from its law school in 1941. Brent served as a naval intelligence officer during World War II. He began his law practice in Richmond in 1946 and became partner with the firm that became Christian, Barton, Epps, Brent & Chappell. He was active in community service in Richmond for four decades -- including work in the 1960s as chairman of the Greater Metropolitan Association, an organization formed to promote a Richmond-Henrico merger. In the 1970s he was a member of VCU's Board of Visitors (appointed in 1968, the year the university was founded) and president of the Downtown Development Unlimited, an organization that promoted private investment in the downtown Richmond. He also served as director and president of the Metropolitan Richmond Chamber of Commerce. He was also active in his church, St. James Episcopal Church in Richmond, serving terms as vestryman and warden. He died June 8, 1996.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of documents concerning Downtown Development Unlimited and Project One, Henrico County Annexation, RPI Foundation, RMA, Richmond Chamber of Commerce and the Greater Metropolitan Committee. The collection dates from the early 1960s through the early 1980s.
Eight volume bound set of court proceedings of the 1941 Annexation of Henrico by Richmond transferred to book collection.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The arrangement follows the donors folder endings and has been grouped according to general topic and alphabetically therein.
Organization
Series I--Downtown Development Unlimited (n.d., 1975-1987) Subseries A--Project One (n.d., 1971-1982)
Series II--Richmond Metropolitan Authority (n.d., 1967-1988)
Series III--Annexation of Henrico (n.d., 1961-1970)
Series IV--Richmond Chamber of Commerce (n.d., 1960-1976)
Series V--Richmond Professional Institute Foundation (n.d., 1970-1976)
Series VI--Greater Metropolitan Committee (n.d., 1960-1961)
Contents List
- Series I--Downtown Development Unlimited, n.d. 1975-1987
  - Agendas (Miscellaneous) 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Brochures (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Central Richmond Association (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Commission minutes 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Correspondence and General File 1 1975 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Correspondence and General File 2 1975 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Correspondence and General File 1 1976 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Correspondence and General File 2 1976 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Credits-Disbursements 1977-1984 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Development Packaging Contracts 1977 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Directors, Officers and Executive Committee (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Financial Advisory Committee (Box-folder 1.12)
  - General and Correspondence 1975 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - General and Correspondence 1976 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - General and Correspondence 1977 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - General and Correspondence 1977 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - General and Correspondence 1978 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - General and Correspondence 1979 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - General and Correspondence 1980 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - General and Correspondence 1981 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - General and Correspondence 1982 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - HINES 1976-1978 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Notices 1975-1981 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Orientation Mtg., Articles of Inc., Bylaws of Central Atlanta Progress, Inc. (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Oxford Group 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Penitentiary Removal (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Penitentiary (State) Study 1983-1987 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - SubSeries A--Project One
    - Affirmative Action 1981 (Box-folder 2.5)
    - Background and Description of Project One, Proposals and Plans (4 files) (Box-folder 2.6)
    - Background information on downtown development in other cities, developers' proposals and brochures newspaper and magazine articles (Box-folder 2.7)
    - Background proposals, brochures, newspaper and magazine articles (5 files) (Box-folder 2.8)
    - Best Products 1978 (Box-folder 2.9)
    - Bond Validation 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2.10)
    - City Lease 1977 (Box-folder 2.11)
    - Correspondence and General (1) 1977 (Box-folder 2.12)
    - Correspondence and General (2) 1977 (Box-folder 3.1)
    - Correspondence and General 1978 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - Correspondence and General 1979 (Box-folder 3.3)
    - Correspondence and General 1980 (Box-folder 3.4)
    - Correspondence and General 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - Franklin Federal Parking Garage 1980 (Box-folder 3.6)
    - Hilton Hotels (Box-folder 3.7)
    - Legal Documents and Memoranda (Box-folder 3.8)
    - Legal Documents and Memoranda (Box-folder 3.9)
    - Legal Documents and Memoranda (Box-folder 3.10)
    - Legal Documents and Memoranda (Box-folder 3.11)
    - Office Building 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3.12)
    - Office Building Lease Backup, n.d. (Box-folder 3.13)
    - Parking 1981 (Box-folder 3.14)
    - Philip Morris 1979 (Box-folder 3.15)
    - Proposals and Plans (3 files) (Box-folder 3.16)
    - Proposals and Plans (2 files) (Box-folder 4.1)
    - Presentation, n.d. (Box-folder 4.2)
- Series II--Richmond Metropolitan Authority
  - Annual Report 1986 (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Annual Report 1987 (Box-folder 4.4)
  - Annual Report 1988 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - Correspondence No. 6 (6 files) 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4.6)
  - Downtown Expressway No. 98 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Estimated revenues Alternative Tollway Systems 1967 (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Finances #33 (4 files) 1967-1973 (Box-folder 4.9)
  - Historic Sites--National Register: James River and Kanawha Canal (Box-folder 4.10)
  - Historic Sites--National Register: Treatises (Box-folder 5.1)
  - James River and Kanawha Canal Co. (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Acts of Assembly (Box-folder 5.3)
  - C and O Plat (Box-folder 5.4)
  - City Baseline Plats (Box-folder 5.5)
  - Reports and Papers (Box-folder 5.6)
  - Richmond-Petersburg Plat (Box-folder 5.7)
  - Title Notes (Box-folder 5.8)
  - Land Acquisition-Applicability of SS. 8-673 to Condemnation Procedures (Box-folder 5.9)
  - Landscaping Correspondence (Box-folder 5.10)
  - Meadow Street Extension #72 1972-1976 (Box-folder 5.11)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 5.12)
  - Files 1-4 (Box-folder 5.13)
  - Metropolitan Richmond...Location Factors, n.d. (Box-folder 5.14)
  - Minutes, Notices and Agenda (4 files) 1966-1974 (Box-folder 5.15)
  - Official Statement 38 (2 files) 1967-1971 (Box-folder 5.16)
  - Original Legal Documents (Box-folder 5.17)
  - Plan of Government for the Richmond Region A Survey Report 1959 (Box-folder 5.18)
  - Reports and Publicity #17 (4 files) 1964-1966 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - Richmond Expressway System Biennium Inspection Report 1984, 1986, 1988 (Box-folder 6.2)
  - Richmond First Clut (2 files) 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6.3-6.4)
  - Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike Authority (4 files) 1964-1970 (Box-folder 6.5-6.8)
  - Powhite Extension #83 1973-1977 (Box-folder 6.9)
  - Proposed Richmond Expressway System Traffic and Revenues 1966 (Box-folder 6.10)
  - Richmond Streetscape, n.d. (Box-folder 6.11)
  - Shuttle Bus #69 (Box-folder 6.12)
  - Time Schedules (Box-folder 6.13)
  - Western Expressway and Belt Line River Crossing Engineering Report 1963 (Box-folder 6.14)
- Series III--Annexation of Henrico
  - Active/Non-Active Workers and Volunteers (Box-folder 7.1)
  - Annexation Suit (Box-folder 7.2)
  - Biographies (Box-folder 7.3)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box-folder 7.4)
  - City Exhibits (Box-folder 7.5)
  - City Exhibits (Box-folder 7.6)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 7.7)
  - Criticisms (Box-folder 7.8)
  - Dawson, John Constitutional Amendment #51 1970 (Box-folder 7.9)
  - Editorials, merger facts (Box-folder 7.10)
  - General Information 1961 (Box-folder 7.11)
  - Greater Metropolitan Committee (Box-folder 7.12)
  - LeGrand, J.R. Testimony (Box-folder 7.13)
  - Map Showing Acreage (Box-folder 7.14)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. 1963 (Box-folder 7.15)
  - Motion to Reconsider Metes and Bounds of Territory Pleadings (Box-folder 7.16)
  - Posters, Flyers and bumper stickers (Box-folder 7.17)
  - Questions asked of Mr. Browning and Mr. Dunn at Brookland Civic Center 11/1/61 (Box-folder 7.18)
  - Schools, John A. Testimony (Box-folder 7.19)
  - Smith, John W. Testimony (Box-folder 7.20)
  - State Senators, Delegates and Legislators (Box-folder 7.21)
  - Suit brought by Independent Taxpayers Assn. (Box-folder 7.22)
  - Tax Effect of Merger 1961 (Box-folder 7.23)
  - Trapnell, William H. Testimony (Box-folder 7.24)
  - Witnesses (2 files) (Box-folder 7.25-7.26)
  - Women's Division Citizens for Merger Research Committee (Box-folder 7.27)
- Series IV--Richmond Chamber of Commerce
  - Bulletins-Notices (2 files) (Box-folder 8.1-8.2)
  - Correspondence 1965-1968 (Box-folder 8.3)
  - Correspondence (2 files) 1968 (Box-folder 8.4-8.5)
  - Correspondence 1969 (Box-folder 8.6)
  - General (4 files) 1967 (Box-folder 8.7-8.10)
  - Industrial Financing Committee 1960-1961 (Box-folder 8.11)
  - Minutes--Executive Committee and Board 1967 (Box-folder 8.12)
  - Richmond Chamber of Commerce (3 files) 1969-1970 (Box-folder 8.13-8.15)
  - Headquarters Committee 1976-1977 (Box-folder 8.16)
  - Nominating Committee 1976 (Box-folder 8.17)
  - Post Opinion (Box-folder 8.18)
  - Route 64, n.d. (Box-folder 8.19)
  - Transportation Committee 1973-1974 (Box-folder 8.20)
- Series V--Richmond Professional Institute Foundation
  - RPI Foundation (5 files) 1970-1976 (Box-folder 9.1-9.5)
- Series VI--Greater Metropolitan Committee
  - Agenda 1961 (Box-folder 9.6)
  - Clean Up, n.d. 1962 (Box-folder 9.7)
  - Continuation 1961 (Box-folder 9.8)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous (3 files) 1961 (Box-folder 9.9-9.11)
  - General Information (2 files) (Box-folder 9.12-9.13)
  - Miscellaneous (5 files) 1961 (Box-folder 9.14-9.18)
  - Records Volume 1961 (Box-folder 9.19)
  - Richmond-Henrico Merger Committee 1960-1961 (Box-folder 9.20)